the room was dark dank uh it was
depressing in there the patient was
asking how much longer he had to live it
was just it just felt like a room full
of depression and so I had raised the
blind up in that room told him that we
needed to get more light in and then I
realized that this was probably not
going to be enough we needed to do more
for him so I talked to our respiratory
therapists because I knew that we needed
to get him outside in the sudden there's
this little area in our hospital with
nice trees and plants and it's uh it's
protected around from the wind as you
can see there uh this particular day it
was It was kind of partly cloudy but
there was Sun that was coming out and I
really felt in it it really moved me
that we needed to get this gentleman
outside so I wrote an order in the chart
that he needed to get full sunlight
every day for 20 to 30 minutes and our
respiratory therapist was just so
resourceful in getting two oxygen tanks
together combining it to get this
gentleman on enough oxygen to get
outside and away from the hospital and
that's what we did and so that happened
on that very first day and I went home
thinking well let's see if this works I
mean according to the studies it seems
as though near infrared radiation should
work people used this a 100 years ago
what's the risk of doing it now let's
let's try
it hello living Mana church members so
good to have you here on true Health
Tuesday so this is coming into the
height of the flu season so we're going
to talk today about viruses not just the
flu but also covid is making a
Resurgence and all sorts of viruses and
and it's very clear as to why this
happens in December every year like
clockwork and it has to do with sunlight
and we're going to talk a little bit
more about that
today so if we look at what happens
every single year you can see very
clearly that there are these Peaks that
go up and down in influenza deaths per
year and notice that the influenza
deaths are right
after the sun is the lowest in the sky
so in other words it's January that
we're seeing the Peaks and you can see
this very clearly it's it's not uh it's
it's not something that you would miss
easily here and you can see this this is
very clearly what the situation is in
terms of flu deaths per week in the
United
States if you remember with covid-19
they showed that in fact the surge in
Europe uh during 2020 was not related to
temperature of the country was not
related to humidity but was actually
related to the latitude so another words
the higher you were up on the globe like
in Finland down here that's the first
countries that actually
got the uh The covid Surge during 2020
so Finland Sweden
Russia Great Britain all the way down in
the South finally at the very end which
was
Greece and we went over these studies
before as well but again what they did
here on this study that was published in
the British Journal of Dermatology was
they looked at the parts of the United
States and England and Italy that could
not get enough vitamin D in the
wintertime and they found that even in
those places where there was no vitamin
D being made because it was so far north
in the winter time there was still a
difference between those that live
towards the South and those that live
toward the north indicating that there
was something other than vitamin
D that was beneficial in sunlight
towards
covid-19 and it caused them to say that
given that the effect appears
independent of a vitamin D pathway it
suggests possible new covid-19
therapies I teamed up with Margaret
scutch and she is a professor of
geography at the Universidad National
autonoma in Mexico and she and I
published this paper looking at exactly
that type of of uh theory is that when
you look around the world in countries
that have a high proportion of people
with an elevated BMI that those which
had less sunlight so these these dark
red areas up here this would be cluster
4 high BMI and medium deaths versus
those that are a little bit closer to
the these orange ones which is cluster 3
also had a high BMI but they had lower
deaths and we believe this is related to
sun
exposure this was a study that was
published as well and it shows that
infrared light which is a component of
sunlight actually it's the majority of
sunlight is in the infrared region
actually uh does something to sells on a
petri dish it actually alleviates or
relieves a mechanism of
hyperinflammation called tlr4 which is
toik receptor 4 it's a very complicated
uh system but this is the system that
has been shown to be hyper revved up in
patients with covid-19 so in a Petri
dish we can see that infrared light at
least at the cellular level does have an
effect on cells um in terms of ramping
down inflammation that you might get in
covid-19 the question of course is is
does it actually work in human beings
right we don't care about cells on Petri
dishes we want to know is this going to
work in cells in the human body and uh
to do that you would need to have a very
well randomized controlled trial where
you take people who have covid for
instance in this case and uh you bring
them into the hospital and you treat
them and you do something to one group
that you don't do to the other group but
ideally it would be a randomized and
controlled and blinded study that's hard
to do especially when you're taking care
of patients uh but that's exactly what
they did this was a very well-designed
study and it was actually published in a
very prestigious Journal called the
Journal of photochemistry and
photobiology uh specifically in biology
has the impact factor of 6.2 which for
those of you who don't understand and
know this this puts it in the top 5% of
respected journals in its field so this
is a pretty notable study and what they
did in this study which was prettying
amazing was
they took patients with covid-19 and
exposed them using a jacket that had LED
lights on the inside pretty high density
and gave them this near infrared
radiation so you're probably thinking
well what's the point of that the skin
is going to stop that light the body is
not going to even know that there's
infrared radiation going through them
well that's the interesting thing about
near infrared light is near infrared
light can can penetrate through the
atmosphere at any angle and it can
penetrate through a few layers of your
clothing to get deep down into your
system and uh in fact some Studies have
shown that 70 to 80% of the cells in
your body actually can quote see near
infrared light that is coming from uh
any Source including the
sun I mean that's why they did the study
uh these people are not uh idiots right
so they know that this light can
actually penetrate through I was
recently given a photograph from Dr
Robert Fosbury who is an astrophysicist
at uh the European Space Agency where he
actually took a picture of his hand and
you could see uh a light source behind
the sand which was uh behind the hand
which was infrared and this was an
infrared photograph and you could
clearly see the light going through his
hand very very easily uh so this is type
of light can actually penetrate through
tissues there's no question if you want
to think about this in a different way
think about a car pulling up to you next
to you and they're playing very loud
music now you're not going to hear that
music the same in your car next to the
car that's playing the music but rather
you're going to hear predominantly low
frequency sounds and that's because low
frequency energy can penetrate through
things very very easily and near
infrared radiation is in the lower
frequency the longer wavelength spectrum
of the uh of the solar Spectrum so yes
so the key thing to understand here is
that it could do it it can go through so
what did they find they found that these
patients who were given this near
infrared radiation were actually
discharged from the hospital 4 days
earlier and they um they were able
to have better pulmonary function
testing they had better hematological
standards this was a small study there
was only about 30 people in that uh
study but the effects were so powerful
that they were statistically significant
um it wasn't powerered for mortality and
it didn't show that there was a a change
in mortality but imagine if this was uh
done it's interesting to think that
perhaps giving INF infrared radiation
would give you this type of mortality
like we have here in the summer for the
flu and taking it away we would have
this kind of mortality like we do in the
wintertime for the flu and I just want
to show you that it's not just the flu
that is related to sunlight look at this
this is actually a map of deaths per
week in the United States from heart
disease cancer obviously covid-19 here
in 2020 stroke um chronic lower
respiratory diseases Alzheimer's disease
diabetes influenza kidney disease notice
that just about all of these
diseases undulate with the season okay
and we've already shown you that it
didn't have much to do with humidity or
temperature but it did track very well
with latitude and so I do believe that
the Sun and sunlight is driving this the
the sad thing is that Americans spend
only about 93% sorry about only 7% of
their waking hours outside 93% is inside
uh kind of
interesting you may notice interestingly
that the one thing that actually Trends
the opposite direction are accidents and
we know that in the summertime there are
more accidents in the summer because
people are traveling more and things of
that nature but uh that's the one thing
that bucks the trend all of these
natural causes of death though due peak
in
December and
January and let's not forget that this
is what people did you know hundreds of
years ago um here is or at least 100
years ago during the 1918 pandemic in
the advena sanitariums in the Northeast
they used hydrotherapy which we've
talked about before fresh air sleep rest
sunshine and comparison to the Army
hospitals there was a significant uh
reduction in influenza deaths that only
only 2% went on to get pneumonia in the
adventus sanitariums 16% uh pneumonia
versus um uh here in the Army hospitals
which used a lot of aspirin and kept
their patients pretty much inside for
the most part and you can see here
photographic proof of what we used to do
100 Years Ago by getting patients
outside onto the rooftops or if they
actually had built it into their system
as you can see here here you can see
here on the left these were surgical
cases and the senior girls it say here
that were going
outside they noticed that the Sun and
healing actually uh improved when
patients were outside in the sun you can
see they're basking in the
sunlight so knowing all of this um it
was unusual for me to see covid patients
in the last year or so but there was one
that came in very recently to my
Hospital who was pretty severe and I was
asked to see him and uh knowing all of
this information I was very motivated to
get him outside let me tell you a little
bit about about his case especially now
that we have a number of patients that
are like this so this is a gentleman
that at a different hospital with an
orthopedic issue on day one was
diagnosed with covid incidentally
because he was having some mild symptoms
and at that time he was started on some
dexamethasone but he developed a
reaction to it and wouldn't take it for
another day or so um by day seven his
issue with the orthopedic issue was
resolved and and at least getting better
and so he was discharged home however by
day 11 his covid symptoms were getting
worse and he actually came into our
hospital at four liters nasal canel
nasal canel is one of these simple
things that people put on to get oxygen
um and the next day by day 12 he had
already gone up to a 10 L oxymizer which
is one of these devices that gives more
oxygen and this is when he was admitted
to the hospital he was started on
solumedrol a ziyin and they dced the
Tylenol at that
time by the next day he was again on 10
L maximizer I had still not yet been
called to see this patient because I
work in the Intensive Care Unit and I
don't get called unless patients are
very very severe so you can imagine I I
was called on day 14 since he was
diagnosed with covid at that time he
jumped to 35 lers 100% F2 on high flow
and that's a device that looks like this
and it's pumping quite a bit of oxygen
into the nose again 100% oxygen this is
this is pretty much uh as high as you
can go with with conventional oxygen
therapy before you get into ventilation
or even non-invasive ventilation so
BiPAP or even getting put on a
ventilator so at this point I was called
to see the patient I went into his room
after I had gowned up put on a a hat n95
mask the room was dark dank uh it was
depressing in there the patient was
asking how much longer he had to live it
was just it just felt like a room full
of depression and so I had raised the
blind up in that room told him that we
needed to get more light in and then I
realized that this was probably not
going to be enough we needed to do more
for him so I talked to our respiratory
therapists because I knew that we needed
to get him outside in the sun there's
this little area in our hospital with
nice trees and plants and it's uh it's
protected around from the wind as you
can see there uh this particular day it
was It was kind of partly cloudy but
there was Sun that was coming out and I
really felt in it it really moved me
that we needed to get this gentleman
outside so I wrote an order in the chart
that he needed to get full sunlight
every day for 20 to 30 minutes and our
respiratory therapist was just so
resourceful in getting two oxygen tanks
together combining it to get this
gentleman on enough oxygen to get
outside and away from the hospital and
that's what we did and so that happened
on that very first day and I went home
thinking well let's see if this works I
mean according to the studies it seems
as though near infrared radiation should
work people used this 100 years ago
what's the risk of doing it now let's
let's try it and as you can see here
that uh the solumedrol these medications
that were started back here on day 12
which is the standard of care which I
would do on anyone and still would do on
anyone you can see here that despite
this the patient was getting worse when
we instituted full sunlight for 20 to 30
minutes you can see almost immediately
there was a change from 35 L at 100%
oxygen down to 15 L the next day and the
day after that went down to 10 L
oxymizer 6 L 4 L and then finally the
patient was discharged by day 19 and
actually went home without any need for
supplemental oxygen I'll also tell you
that uh Not only was I meeting the
physical needs of this patient but when
I went into that room and I talked to
that patient we also had a prayer and we
uh prayed about his condition and um and
that uh he would that his condition was
not only in the hands of the doctors but
the doctors are are the hands of God and
so um we we were all working together
for his benefit and uh you know I
believe that that actually also had some
benefit as well so full sunlight in
addition notice we did not stop Sol
Medrol we did not stop the ziy um that
that he was started on WE continued
those things because I firmly believe
that uh we really ought to be doing
everything that we know uh is beneficial
and we know from the UK recovery R trial
that dexamethazone uh is beneficial in
these patients unfortunately we could
not use that because he had a reaction
to it he did not have a reaction to the
solumedrol so we kept that on board and
so actually this is a picture of that
very first day that he went outside I I
uh I was just compelled to take a
picture um I did ask for their
permission and they gave me permission
to use this Photograph uh I called him
up about a week or two later he was um
still recovering from this Orthopedic
situation ation but was feeling much
better and he uh he told me something
very interesting you know he told me
that first day that he was very
depressed but that when he got out as
you can see right here this is him in in
the wheelchair that he said that that
sun on him felt so good to get outside
and as you can see uh you know this is
this is anecdotal but you can see that
the oxygen improved dramatically I
cannot prove that sunlight worked
because of this case report because case
reports don't prove anything
but uh I was convinced by the evidence
of what I saw in the studies studies
that were published showing this and I
have to say that it's very gratifying to
see that uh research can actually have
an effect on
individuals so I am fairly convinced
that we need to have hospitals that
allow sunlight I think sunlight is very
very powerful um there have been many
studies that have shown that people who
get sunlight when they're in the
hospital they just do better when
there's hospital rooms that have two
beds one bed closer to the door the
other bed closer to the window the
patient in the window bed seems to do
better seems to get out statistically
significantly faster has less mortality
rate all of these Studies have shown
that sunlight is very very
beneficial so I do really think that we
ought to start rethinking our stance on
Hospital architecture I really do think
that we need to get patients outside
more and until we can make some real
changes in how that happens uh that we
ought to be thinking about getting
patients outside for 20 to 30 minutes a
day if it's
possible so what can we do for ourselves
I think we need to be a champion uh if
you're a healthcare worker at your
hospital for sunlight if not if you have
a family member who's hospitalized or
taking care of someone who's sick
encourage them to get outside into the
sun if it's safe um the best time to do
this is anytime uh do it when you can uh
especially now in the winter time when
the sun is not very high sometimes your
choices are pretty limited but get out
there uh you need to learn about the
science about sunlight for ill patients
start to read up on it start to become
facil with it and then you got to
practice yourself what you preach so get
out there now people might ask you what
is it that you do and then you can tell
them what you do educate your colleagues
uh move the cause use your clout use
your your resources share this video
share other videos and uh I would have
to say that you know if hospitals are
smart and they are financially
responsible for the health care of their
patients which is becoming increasingly
clear uh they are going to do everything
that they can to make sure that their
patients are healthy they're that
they're discharged and they don't come
back as a bounceback in other words and
they don't come back uh sick and uh
that's going to be financially rewarding
not only for the hospital but it's also
going to be very rewarding in terms of
health for the patient and that's really
what counts so um my my message to you
during this 2023
2024 season when the sun is low and
there's rest viruses all around us is
one of the things that you can do one of
the biggest things that you can do very
easily very easily that will improve
your health and your resistance against
respiratory diseases is to get outside
and get at least 20 to 30 minutes of
sunlight every day that is key because
uh unfortunately a lot of us work we get
up in the morning before the sun comes
up and we are home after the sun goes
down and at our work we don't go outside
and I think this is mental so uh do this
and encourage others to do the
same so for True Health Tuesdays this is
Dr Roger schwell signing off thanks for
joining us